Guide to the Bonsall family papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Bonsall Family Papers,
1683-1916
[Bulk Dates:1825-1875].
Bonsall Family.
2.5 linear ft. (6 document boxes, 1 oversized folder)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0132
4079363
The papers of the Bonsall Family of Pennsylvania primarily consist of correspondence, personal and professional documents, journals, genealogical tables, photographs, and a family Bible. The majority of the letters, documents, and journals were generated by or for Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879) and the members of his immediate family, particularly his eldest son, Spencer Bonsall (1816-1888). Also included are documents produced by or for other Bonsall family members, from Richard Bonsall who settled in Philadelphia with William Penn (ca. 1683) to Eleanor Crosby Martin Bonsall (1894-?), the daughter of William Martin Bonsall and granddaughter of Spencer Bonsall.
Historical Note
The Bonsall family traces its North American ancestry back to Richard Bonsall (d. 1699), who left England with William Penn around the year 1683 to settle in Pennsylvania. Over the course of their history, the Bonsalls remained devoted members of the Religious Society of Friends, also known as the Quakers. Well into the nineteenth century, much of their correspondence retained the use of "thee" and "thou" that were characteristic of Quaker plain speech, while months and days usually appeared in numeric rather than named form (for example, "1st month, 4th day= January 4") to disassociate them from pagan deities. Throughout the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, most of the Bonsalls continued to reside in the Delaware Valley, especially in the areas surrounding Philadelphia, Germantown, and Chester, but, as the country began to expand westward, others moved out to Ohio, Illinois, and Colorado. The Bonsall heirs were chiefly occupied by real estate, transportation, surveying, and the law, from which they seem to have derived a comfortable, if not extravagant, living. A great part of the material in the collection concerns Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879) and his oldest son, Spencer Bonsall (1816-1888). The family of Spencer's wife, Ellen Crosby Martin, is also well represented.
Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879): Edward H. Bonsall was born in 1794 to Isaac Bonsall (1765-1831) and Mercy Milhous (1768-1805) of Philadelphia. His career as a conveyancer engaged him in the founding of the Philadelphia, Germantown and Norristown Railroad, of which he eventually became president. In addition to being an avid writer of letters, speeches, and poems, Bonsall was an active member of several learned and charitable organizations, including the Philadelphia Literary Association and the Society for Alleviating the Miseries of Public Prisons. As revealed in a number of his writings, he also nurtured a lifelong interest in travel. His detailed travel notes record the history, surroundings, and landscape of various cities in Europe, Egypt, and a burgeoning industrial America. These accounts frequently incorporate records of his day-to-day travel arrangements and expenses.
Spencer Bonsall (1816-1888): Spencer Bonsall, the first son of Edward H. Bonsall and Lydia McIlvain (1795-1854), inherited his father's love for travel and history. He was educated at the Quaker Westtown Boarding School in Chester, Pennsylvania, where, as his correspondence reveals, he lived an active social life. After an apprenticeship to the druggist Samuel C. Sheppard, Spencer took a trip around the world, passing through Madeira, Portugal, and landing in Calcutta, India. In 1840, he returned to India where he secured a position with the Assam Tea Company. Upon his return to the United States eight years later, he became the principal surveyor for the city of Philadelphia, and shortly thereafter, in 1854, married Ellen Crosby Martin. Upon the outbreak of the Civil War, Spencer enlisted in the 81st Pennsylvania infantry as a hospital steward, where he served from 1861 until 1863 when he was slightly wounded at the Battle of Gettysburg. From 1869 to 1883 he served as an assistant librarian and genealogist at the Historical Society of Pennsylvania.
Scope and Content
The Bonsall Family Papers primarily consist of correspondence, personal and professional documents, journals, genealogical tables, photographs, and a family Bible. The majority of the letters, documents, and journals were generated by or for Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879) and the members of his immediate family, particularly his eldest son, Spencer Bonsall (1816-1888).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1818-1901, [Bulk dates 1824-1878]
Series II: Documents, 1683-1916
Series III: Journals, Account Books, and Composition Books, 1785-1865
Series IV: Family Bible, 1814 (with notes dating 1815-1876)
Subjects
Assam Company.; Westtown Boarding School.; United States.--Army.--Pennsylvania Infantry Regiment, 81st (1861-1865).; Bonsall, Edward H., 1794-1879.; Bonsall, Richard.; Bonsall, Spencer, 1816-1888.; Bonsall, Spencer, 1816-1888--Diaries.; Penn, William, 1644-1718.; Egypt--Description and travel.; India--Description and travel.; Germantown (Philadelphia, Pa.)--Social life and customs.; Madeira (Madeira Islands)--Description and travel.; Pennsylvania--Social life and customs.; Pennsylvania--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal narratives.; Pennsylvania--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Regimental histories.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Hospitals.; United States--Description and Travel--Diaries.; Families--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia.; Hospitals--United States--Employees--Diaries.; Quakers--Correspondence.; Quakers--Family relationships.; Quakers--Pennsylvania--Diaries.; Quakers--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia--Social life and customs.; Railroads--United States--History--19th century.; Soldiers--Health and hygiene--United States--History--19th century.; Tea--India.; Travel literature--India.; Photoprints.; Tintypes.; Poetry.; Genealogies.; Silhouettes.; Calling cards.; Deeds.; Indentures.; Playbills.; Marriage licenses.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1952 M-52 Robinson, Cedric L. Purchase
- Series I: Correspondence, 1818-1901 [Bulk Dates 1824-1878]
  This series, which comprises approximately half of the collection, contains correspondence by and to various members of the Bonsall and Martin families. Most of the letters were generated by or to Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879) and are personal in nature, although a small number concern Bonsall's career as a conveyancer and railroad industrialist. Substantial correspondence exists between Edward H. Bonsall and his son, Joseph Bonsall (1833-1876); and between Edward H. Bonsall and John Ousley Bonsall, a distant relative living in Ireland. The collection also contains several letters written by or to Spencer Bonsall when he was a student at the Westtown School in Chester, Pennsylvania. The Martin family is represented by several letters between William Martin, Esq. (1797-1862); his wife, Sarah Ann Martin (née Smith); and their daughter, Ellen Crosby Martin, wife of Spencer Bonsall.
  - Biddle, [Craig?] to Spencer Bonsall, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bonsall, Anna to Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879), 1855 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    (includes correspondence by Jane M. Plummer)
    - Bonsall, Charles, 1832-1871 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      (includes letter from "Laura" to Mary Bonsall)
    - Bonsall, Edward H. (1794-1879), 1824-1876, (3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 4 to 6)
    - Bonsall, Edward H. (1821-1841), 1831-1836 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (includes correspondence by Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879) and Henry Bonsall)
      - Bonsall, Eleanor Crosby Martin to Santa Claus, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Bonsall, Henry to Spencer Bonsall, 1831-1832 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Bonsall, Jeremiah, 1833-1847 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        (includes correspondence by Lydia M. Bonsall)
      - Bonsall, John Ousley to Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879), 1837-1870 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Bonsall, Joseph H., 1859-1875 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Bonsall, Spencer, 1833-1854 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Boustead, James to Spencer Bonsall, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Brewster, A.W. to Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879), 1876 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Castle, J. H. to Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879), 1859 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Chandler, Joseph R. to Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879), 1878 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Clark, S. J. to Ellen C. Martin, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Cope, Marmaduke C. to Mary Ann C. Morris, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        (extract in the hand of Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879))
      - [Duttan?] Samuel to Spencer Bonsall, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Egner, Emma C. to Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879), 1876 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Hollinshead, Ray M. to Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879), 1824 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Hoopes, Edward C. to Spencer Bonsall, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Horner, Joseph P. to Joseph Hartshorne, 1836 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Johnson, Rowland to Spencer Bonsall, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Kite, Thomas to Spencer Bonsall, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Lightfoot, H. M. to Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879), 1839 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Martin, Georgiana, [1852?] (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Martin, John Hill to Ellen C. Martin, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Martin, Sarah A., 1852-1853 (Box 2, Folder 15)
        (includes correspondence by William M. Martin, 1853)
      - Martin, William, M. (1797-1862),1844-1853 (Box 2, Folder 16)
        (includes correspondence by Sarah A. Martin, 1853)
      - Moynan, Harriette E. to Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879), 1873 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Moynan, Richard to Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879), 1876 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Newman, Henry to Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879), 1858 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Pease, Jonathan, 1836-1860 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Plummer, Jane M., 1818-1872 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Price, Isaac C. to Spencer Bonsall, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Rhodes, C. D. to Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879), 1876-1877 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Smith, Ellen C. to William M. Smith, 1852 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Snider, Annie L. to Ellen C. Martin, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Stokes, Hannah M. to Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879), 1872 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Tatum, Josiah to Spencer Bonsall, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Thompson, Joseph B. to Spencer Bonsall, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Warrington, Priscilla to Jane M. Plummer, 1831 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Wilson, Susan to Spencer Bonsall, 1831 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Wood, M. A. to Mary B. Hutchin, 1838 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Woodnutt, Preston to Spencer Bonsall, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Series II: Documents and Photographs, 1683-1916
  This series, which comprises most of the remainder of the collection, contains a broad range of documents relating to several generations of the Bonsall family. The largest portion consists of ancestral wills, land deeds, and other property records, dating from the seventeenth to the nineteenth centuries. Also well represented are genealogical tables and coats of arms. Personal documents, such as poems, calling cards, tickets, and invitations, are interspersed with professional membership certificates, speeches, writings, and general memoranda. Dozens of photographs, tintypes, and silhouettes depict members of the Bonsall and Martin families, some of which have been annotated by William Martin Bonsall, the son of Spencer Bonsall and Ellen Crosby Martin. A small number of documents pertain to individuals with an uncertain relationship to the Bonsall family, while a few others are anonymous. A map of the Denver, Colorado area by Joseph H. Bonsall, dated August 22, 1871, has been moved to the Historical Map Collection.
  - General, 1805-1909 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    (includes envelopes, poems, tickets, newspaper clippings, a political cartoon, and other miscellaneous documents)
  - Aston, Peter and Hannah--Land Deed to Thomas Guest, 1751 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    (includes release of claims on Thomas Guest for above indenture by Isaac Greenleaf and Mordecai Yarnall)
  - Bonsall, Benjamin--Copies of Will and Land Deed to Josiah Fearne, 1729-1768 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bonsall, Benjamin Say--Printed Jury List, 1833 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bonsall, Edward H. (1739-1826)--Land Deed, Will, and Estate Settlement, 1798-1830 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bonsall, Edward H. (1794-1879), 1826-1879 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    ((includes business reports, travel accounts, orations, passport, an account of the death of Edward H. Bonsall Jr.(1821-1841), and other personal and professional documents)
  - Bonsall, Eleanor Crosby Martin, 1894-1898 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    (includes drawings, hair, and religious cards)
  - Bonsall, Ellen C. (Martin)--Receipt, 1877 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bonsall, Enoch--Copy of Marriage Certificate, 1717 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Bonsall, Isaac--Marriage Certificate and Estate Documents, 1786-circa 1830 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Bonsall, Jacob, Benjamin and Enoch--Copy of Land Grant from William Penn, 1703 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    (includes envelope addressed to Spencer Bonsall, Historical Society of Pennsylvania)
  - Bonsall, James--Will, 1754 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Bonsall, John Ousley--Poem on the Death of his Wife, 1869 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Bonsall, Mary (Mrs. John Ousely)--Poem to her Husband, 1860 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Bonsall, Mary H.--Land Title Brief, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Bonsall, Mercy--Poems, 1788-1789 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Bonsall, Richard--Copy of Will, 1699 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Bonsall, Spencer, 1827-1889 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    (includes receipts, copper plates for calling cards, marriage certificate, professional membership certificates, poem transcriptions, and four undated, unsigned letters)
  - Bonsall, Vincent--Property Documents and Will, 1751-1796 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Bonsall, William Martin, 1867-1911 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    (includes will, tickets, class rosters, invitations, a court summons, and professional membership certificates)
  - Butler, John--Land Deed to Abraham Scott, 1768 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Bonsall Family--Photographs, Silhouettes, Tintypes, 1776-1916, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bonsall Family--Genealogical Research and Coats of Arms, 1761-circa 1870s undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    (includes photocopies gifted by Joseph Colton Bonsall, October 2005)
  - Clarke, John Jr.--Copy of Will, 1731 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Flower, Samuel--Land Deed to John Butler, 1765 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Fraelich, Leonard--Mortgage to Christopher Witt, 1759 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Froth, Henry--Copy of Will, 1836 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Grand Central Variety Theatre--Playbills, 1874-1875 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Guest, Thomas--Indenture to Samuel Flower, Land Deed, 1755 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Hunt, Joseph--Marriage Certificate, 1724 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Jones, Robert--Land Deed to John Butler, 1763 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Martin, E--Invitation from Union League Club, 1886 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Martin, Ellen C.--Certificates of Approbation, 1843 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Martin Family--Coats of Arms, Genealogical Table, circa 1860s undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Martin, John Hill--Engagement Cards, Newspaper Subscription, 1859-1876 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Martin, William (1765-1798)--Receipts, Appraisal of Goods, 1788-1798 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Martin, William M. (1797-1862)--Justice's Commission, Testimonials on Death of, 1836-1862 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Mercantile Library Company, Philadelphia--Library Rules, circa [1855?] (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Milhous, Jane--Poem, 1823 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Pearson, Isaac--Land Deed to Samuel Flower, 1752 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Penn, William--Coat of Arms, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    (includes four miscellaneous coats of arms, undated)
  - Pennsylvania Laws and Statues--Extracts from laws passed between 1698 and 1774, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    (includes envelope addressed to Spencer Bonsall)
  - Penrose, Thomas--Deed to Jane Hales, 1777 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Philadelphia--Wax Seals, 1683-1701 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    (includes two seals of William Penn and one of the city of Philadelphia)
  - Sandilands, James--Copy of Petition to William Penn, 1700 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Scott, Abraham--Land Deed to Robert McMin, 1769 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Wroth, William--Receipt, 1807 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Yarnall, [Mordecai?]--Transcription from the Third Book of Chronicles, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Bonsall, Spencer--Life Membership to the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, 1870 (Box 14-P-2)
  - Bonsall, William M.--Membership to the Veteran Corps of the 1st Infantry National Guard of Pennsylvania, 1894 (Box 14-P-2)
  - Crosby, John--Appointment as Judge to the Court of Common Pleas, Delaware County, Pennsylvania, 1799 (Box 14-P-2)
  - Martin, William--Commission as Captain of the Pennsylvania Artillerists of Delaware County, 1828 (Box 14-P-2)
- Series III: Journals and Account Books, 1785-1865
  The sixteen journals in this series cover a range of topics. Prominent are the travel journals of Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879) and Spencer Bonsall, which describe voyages to Washington DC, the Ohio Valley, and Calcutta, India. The collection also contains a Civil War journal by Spencer Bonsall, written between March 1 and April 17, 1863 during his service as a hospital steward in the 81st Pennsylvania Regiment. Further additions include a book of genealogical tables, the legal journal of John Crosby (written between 1803 and 1816), and a handful of late eighteenth- and early nineteenth-century account books containing the costs for such mundane expenses as rent, hair dressing, and laundry. The collection also contains the composition books of Spencer Bonsall, his mother, Lydia McIlvain, and a Rebecca B. Thomson, whose connection to the family is unclear.
  - Bonsall, Edward H. (1794-1879)--Travel Journals and Letter Books, 1824-1875, (2 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Bonsall Family--Genealogy Book, 1903-1908 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    (covers 1682 to 1866)
  - Bonsall, Mercy--Copy of Writings, 1785-1805 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Bonsall, Spencer, 1832-1863, (3 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 5 to 7)
    (includes composition books, travel journals, Civil War diary; and a poem by Edward H. Bonsall, 1828)
  - Crosby, John--Legal Notebook, 1803-1816 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Martin, William (1765-1799)--Account Book, 1787-1796 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - McIlvain, Lydia--Composition Book, 1812 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Thomson, Rebecca B.--Composition Book, 1824-1826 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Wroth, William and Elizabeth--Account Book, 1794-1824 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    (includes records of James and Mrs. McKeever, and Sarah Thompson)
- Series IV: Family Bible, 1814 (with notes dating 1815-1876)
  This family Bible (Collins's "Quarto" Bible, 3rd ed., NY: printed and sold by Collins and Co., 1814) was owned by Edward H. Bonsall (1794-1879) and lists the marriages, births, diseases, and deaths of his two wives, Lydia Bonsall (née McIlvain) and Mary Bonsall (née Hutchin), as well as his eleven children: Spencer, William Milhous, William, Edward H. Jr., Henry, Jeremiah, Charles, Elizabeth, Jane, Joseph, and Jesse. The Bible is signed and dated at the front: "Edward H. Bonsall 1815."
  - Bible--Collins's Quarto, 3rd edition, New York, 1814 (Box 6, Folder 1)